So, so we begin a new מסכת Masechet today, מסכת מועד קטן,
Masechet Moed Katan, ב׳ עמוד א׳, Beiz amud alef, ב׳, Beiz, today
דף ב׳. Daf Beiz. A few introductory words about this מסכת. masechet.
First of all, interestingly there's a bit of a debate whether the
same way there's a debate about what the last two פרקים prokim
of מגילה Megilla were, what the order was, here there's also a
debate whether מועד קטן Moed Katan is the last tractate of the
of the מסכת masechet or whether חגיגה Chagiga is. Our the normal
assumption is that מועד קטן Moed Katan comes first and then חגיגה
Chagiga although some do have it in the reverse order. The normal
way to know, most people say well what makes more thematic sense,
but actually as scholars have long pointed out, the real order of
the tractates in a סדר seder go by the number of פרקים.
prokim. The point is the problem is that these last two tractates
have the same number of פרקים: prokim: three. So just be aware
there is some debate, but anyway we're going to do מועד קטן
Moed Katan and then חגיגה Chagiga which means we're two months away
from finishing סדר מועד Seder Moed which is which is exciting. And
yet the order would still be the same. That is true. Now
this מסכת masechet is called, you know, מועד קטן, Moed Katan, what
we call it מועד קטן. Moed Katan. A lot of the ראשונים
Rishonim don't call it מועד קטן, Moed Katan, they call it מסכת
משקין Masechet Mashkin based on the first word, which is unusual because
normally you don't have a מסכת masechet called by the first word.
ברכות... Berachot... Alright, that's by chance. But here part of the reason
is because, you know, normally it's called by the theme, but here
there's a mixture of themes. It starts right at the beginning as
we're going to see by certain things that can be done on
חול המועד Chol HaMoed or what are the rules of חול המועד
Chol HaMoed which makes sense after you deal with all of the
חגים, Chagim, you deal with חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, and then חגיגה
Chagiga deals with, you know, the bringing of the קרבן חגיגה Korban
Chagiga which is sort of like some מצוות mitzvos that apply across
the מועדים, moadim, not particular to any particular
מועד, moed, but again a focus on the other sort of like
restrictions and מלאכות melachan and so on, and therefore that's what this
is doing here in this tractate after all of the other sort
of מועדים moadim have been dealt with. At the same time, if
you take just a quick look at the first five words, משקין
בית השלחין במועד ובשביעית, Mashkin beis hashalachin b'moed u'bishvi'is, that a lot
of the things that you can do and not do on חול
המועד Chol HaMoed parallel certain things about what you can and can't
do on the שמיטה. Shmita. So already there's a mixture of themes
there. And in addition to חול המועד Chol HaMoed and שביעית, Shvi'is,
the other big issue that comes up is אבילות, aveilus, okay? And
אלו מגלחין, Elu Megalchin, the third פרק, perek, is pretty much all
about אבילות aveilus and even that is not limited to אבילות, aveilus,
it gets into other issues of נידוי nidui and נזירות nezirus and
so on. Now again there's a tie-in because it starts with ואלו
מגלחין במועד, ve'elu megalchin b'moed, the people that can shave on חול
המועד, Chol HaMoed, but that gets you into questions about well shaving
when what other times somebody doesn't shave, you know, אבילות aveilus and
so on and then it leads to all of these major discussions
of אבילות. aveilus. So the major locus of הלכות אבילות hilchos aveilus
in the גמרא Gemara is in this third פרק. perek. So that's
sort of the topics are basically חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, אבילות, aveilus,
a little שביעית, shvi'is, a little of other things, and hence it's
not surprising that some therefore rather than giving it a more descriptive
name of מועד קטן, Moed Katan, the small מועד moed meaning חול
המועד, Chol HaMoed, call it משקין. Mashkin. But nevertheless it does seem
that the basic sort of framing issues are the חול המועד Chol
HaMoed issues. One other point about this מסכת masechet about the commentaries
etc. that we'll be referring to is as you might have remembered
from a previous מסכתות masechtos when we deal with תענית Taanit and
so on, the whole issue about is רש"י Rashi the real רש"י?
Rashi? And the scholarly consensus was no. There was even a scholarly
consensus that תוספות Tosafos wasn't a normal תוספות, Tosafos, was a very
late תוספות. Tosafos. Here pretty much everybody acknowledges that the רש"י Rashi
is not רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi is about 80% of of of
רבנו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, of commentary of רבנו גרשום. Rabbeinu Gershom. And
what's fascinating is if I hadn't told you that, you might not
have actually realized it
because, you know, it's a pretty much, it's a line-by-line commentary, it's
pretty terse and to the point and clear which is an interesting
thing, you know, when we always sort of say that like רש"י
Rashi was the first one to really do a running commentary on
the גמרא Gemara and so on, I mean it's true in terms
of its comprehensiveness and its clarity and so on, but it's not
like there were no precedents. רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel also, which is
printed on the side, now again רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel is usually
much sparser in terms of what he comments on and not comments
on. But if you get a chance and you want to look
at the what's printed as the רש"י, Rashi, which is really רבנו
גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, you won't you know it'll seem pretty much like
a reasonable, you know, רש"י. Rashi. You might not have fully realized
it. But it's basically 80% רבנו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, 20% taken from
the text we have of רש"י. Rashi. We actually do have the
manuscript of רש"י Rashi and it's been printed in a separate little
book. פירוש רש"י על מסכת מועד קטן. Perush Rashi al Maseches Moed
Katan. Okay, so I thought I had it at home, I couldn't
find it, but I'm pretty sure we have it in the בית
מדרש. Beis Medrash. And the רש"י Rashi on the רי"ף Rif actually,
which normally is not its own manuscript, but normally it is sort
of an editing and a reworking of רש"י Rashi on the גמרא.
Gemara. They print the רש"י Rashi in the רי"ף Rif in the
back. Here in מועד קטן Moed Katan and like I think one
other place, it actually is pretty much from like an accurate witness
to one of the manuscripts of רש"י. Rashi. So actually the better
רש"י Rashi on מועד קטן, Moed Katan, the real רש"י, Rashi, is
to be found more in the רי"ף, Rif, but there actually is
a scholarly edition of it. While we're talking about the רי"ף, Rif,
I should mention that just to make things fun, the ר"ן Ran
on the רי"ף Rif in מועד קטן Moed Katan and as a
general rule is not the ר"ן, Ran, it's נימוקי יוסף. Nimukei Yosef.
So okay, the רש"י Rashi on the רי"ף Rif is the real
רש"י Rashi more than in other מסכתות, masechtos, but the ר"ן Ran
is not the ר"ן. Ran. Anyway, so just to be aware, if
I point out something in רש"י, Rashi, it's really רבינו גרשום. Rabbeinu
Gershom. Okay.
רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom was before. Yeah, before. How well before? Tenth
century. Yeah, I was going to say, I don't know, I know
he was the previous, tenth century, tenth century, you know, eleventh century.
I don't know if it was fifty years or a hundred years.
I don't have the exact date. I don't know, it must be
that the printer did not have, I don't know the history of
that. Could be the printer didn't have the manuscript available to him,
could be the printer had the manuscript of רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom
and thought it was רש"י. Rashi. I don't know.
רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom died in either ten-twenty-eight or ten-forty. רש"י Rashi
died in eleven-oh-five.
Okay, so there you go.
About eighty years. At least their death dates are separated by about
eighty years. Okay, so let's take a look now. Now we begin.
Okay, so משקין בית השלחין במועד, Mashkin beis hashalchin bamoed,
you can irrigate a בית השלחין beis hashalchin on חול המועד. Chol
HaMoed. בית השלחין Beis hashalchin is basically like a field that is
irrigated, but that requires regular irrigation. And therefore if it requires regular
irrigation, by not watering it, you will, you know, the crops are
at serious risk. A field that doesn't require regular irrigation, you know,
as we learned by תענית, Taanis, you know, you need rain, but
there are fields that are much more, the soil is richer, you
know, other types of factors, which I'm sure I'm completely ignorant of,
but that don't require, you know, as much regular water and normally
can be totally fine by the rainfall, is one that's less at
risk. But something that, there are these fields that require, you know,
I mean one of the amazing things that they're doing in developing
countries, right, is new technology to figure out how to, because I
saw this a few years ago when I was in Senegal, about
how to like, you know, with a very minimal amount of water,
but because of just, you know, the amount that they do in
terms of the way they spray it and, you know, doing it
is very precise amount that they can really, it's amazing how much
they can grow crops with a very minimal amount of water if
the technology is right, you know, if they're using exactly the amount
that they need and the way they need it, you know.
You need to take that technology to California today.
Okay, there you go. So anyway, so but obviously water is critical
for crops for fields that need regular irrigation. So here the basic
rule is, is that you can do מלאכה melacha on חול המועד
Chol HaMoed if it's a concern about דבר האבד, davar ha'aved, something
about a loss, a financial loss, or הפסד. hefsed. Okay, now let's
take a look at the
רש"י, Rashi, רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom for this point, just because one
of the important things that we're going to be addressing is what
is the nature of the איסור מלאכה issur melacha on חול המועד.
Chol HaMoed. And that falls into a two types of questions. One
is, not the question of the weight, biblical, rabbinic, what are the
special allowances, but what type of מלאכה melacha is prohibited? When I
say מלאכה melacha on שבת, Shabbos, we've all been well trained to
understand that מלאכה melacha doesn't mean laborious work, it means creative labor
defined by thirty-nine, you know, constructive creative categories, etc. When we say
don't do מלאכה melacha on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, is that what
we mean? Do we mean the ל"ט מלאכות lamed-tes melachos and therefore
any time you allow me to do anything on חול המועד Chol
HaMoed like strike a match I need a היתר heter for it?
Is that what we're talking about? Or do we mean don't do
stuff that's טרחא, tircha, that's laborious, that's effortful? Like that's one question
of what constitutes מלאכה melacha for purposes of חול המועד. Chol HaMoed.
There's another question which is, what is the weight of the prohibition
and therefore is it biblical, is it rabbinic, is it somewhere in
between, what are special cases of allowances and so on? So those
are the two major questions, those or others, but two major questions
that we have to be asking as we go through this מסכתא.
masechta. So let's take a look at רש"י.
Rashi. I'll say we have to be asking, are we going to
encounter the actual source?
Yes,
yes, we will see, there will be these things coming up in
the גמרא, Gemara, but as is usual, it will not, you know,
there'll be a lot of ambiguity about them. But yes, I'm not
just saying them, they'll be rooted in discussions in the גמרא. Gemara.
So let's take a look at רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi says like
this,
רבינו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, whatever. משקין בית השלחין במועד, Mashkin beis hashalchin
bamoed, first one. שדה שהיא עומדת בהר וצריכה להשקותה תמיד משקין אותה
אפילו בחולו של מועד. Sadeh she'hi omedes behar ve'tzricha le'hashkosa tamid mashkin
osa afilu be'cholo shel moed. לפי שהוא הפסד גדול, Lefi she'hu hefsed
gadol, it would be a large loss, so is it any הפסד,
hefsed, הפסד גדול, hefsed gadol, אם אין. im ein.
And a matter of loss the חכמים chachamim allowed you to be
מטריח, matri'ach, so there A you have חכמים chachamim allowing it, and
B you have the emphasis of טירחה, tircha, which doesn't mean the
מלאכה melacha is defined by טירחה, tircha, but it sounds like טירחה
tircha is a big factor here, כמו שאנו מוצאין במסכת חגיגה, k'mo
she-anu motzin b'masechet chagigah,
and now רש״י Rashi quotes a source not interestingly in מועד קטן
Mo'ed Katan but in חגיגה, Chagigah, דכתיב ששת ימים תאכל מצות וביום
השביעי עצרת לה׳ אלקיך מה שביעי עצור בעשיית מלאכה אף ששה אסורים
בעשיית מלאכה. de-chtiv sheshet yamim tochal matzot u-vayom hashvi'i atzeret l'Hashem Elokecha
mah shvi'i atzur ba'asiyat melacha af shisha asurim ba'asiyat melacha. So interestingly,
although the תורה Torah only speaks about not doing מלאכה melacha on
the first day and the seventh day, because they're in the, they,
it puts it in the category of other days, or other days
in its category, you learn from it that מלאכה melacha is also
forbidden on other days. אי מה שביעי עצור בכל מלאכה אף ששה
אסורים בכל מלאכה? i mah shvi'i atzur be-chol melacha af shisha asurim
be-chol melacha? Maybe all מלאכה melacha is forbidden on חול המועד? Chol
HaMoed? תלמוד לומר השביעי שביעי עצור בכל מלאכה, talmud lomar hashvi'i shvi'i
atzur be-chol melacha,
the seventh, only the seventh is fully forbidden, ואין ששה אסורים מכל
מלאכה, v'ein shisha asurim mi-kol melacha, and the other six are not.
Now this sounds very biblical, you're learning it out from a פסוק.
pasuk. לא מסרן הכתוב אלא לחכמים. lo masran hakatuv ela lachachamim.
So the what is forbidden and what is not, that's for the
rabbis to figure out. The verse gave it over to the rabbis.
לא מסרן הכתוב אלא לחכמים lo masran hakatuv ela lachachamim לומר לך
איזו מלאכה אסורה בחולו של מועד ואיזו מותרת, lomar lach eizo melacha
asura b'cholo shel mo'ed v'eizo muteret, ומלאכה שיש בה הפסד אם אינו
עושה אותה, u-melacha sheyesh bah hefsed im eino oseh otah, something that
will have a loss, כמו משקות בית השלחין, k'mo mashkot beit hashalchin,
התירו חכמים, hitiru chachamim, the חכמים chachamim allowed it.
So רש״י Rashi does not for us define what מלאכה melacha is,
what types of מלאכה melacha are אסור. asur. Are they defined by
these ל״ט Lamed Tet categories? Are they defined by טירחה tircha although
he mentions טירחה tircha as their definition? How about the idea that
we make an allowance for דבר האבד? davar ha-aved? Has רש״י Rashi
told us whether מלאכה melacha is biblical or rabbinic on חול המועד?
Chol HaMoed? What do you think? Say again? Has רש״י Rashi told
us whether מלאכה melacha is biblical or rabbinic? No, he hasn't. On
the one hand he quoted פסוקים, pesukim, they sounded like very
biblical-based, real דרשות. drashot. Then he has this phrase, לא מסרן הכתוב
אלא לחכמים, lo masran hakatuv ela lachachamim, and then he said and
therefore the rabbis allowed it. So some could say, oh, so it
means that in the end it's really rabbinic. But it doesn't sound
like that. It sounds like it's some space in between, that the
תורה Torah says there are some things
forbidden, the תורה's Torah saying I'm not going to dictate exactly what
those things are, you the rabbis, you figure out what's constitute what
is included in the biblical prohibitions of חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. So
as opposed to other times where we sort of see it as
all linked to hints in the verse and ultimately we're uncovering what
the verse is either telling us or hinting to us or so
on, here it's like you guys got a blank check, but at
the end of the day, you know, that check is being drawn
on my account, right?
So at the end of the day whatever you fill in, that's
what the תורה Torah is forbidding. That is one way of understanding
it that it really is biblical with a lot of latitude for
the sages. The funny thing is about that approach is that it's
one thing to say I get to figure out the parameters, but
then to say on an ongoing basis I could say and it
could be overridden for reasons A, B, and C, that to override
doesn't sound like included in the general license to define the basic
parameters, right? It's one thing to say okay, I'm going to give
the list of the מלאכות melachot that are forbidden on חול המועד
Chol HaMoed and that then becomes what's biblically forbidden. But then to
say and it could be overridden for this reason or this reason
or that reason, that already makes it sound like something not of
biblical weight, something more like you can have overrides. Okay, and that's
going to be part of this ongoing tension of the nature of
the weight of the איסור מלאכה issur melacha on חול המועד. Chol
HaMoed. I will just point out that there's a parallel discussion by
the עינויים inuyim on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, right? The other things
other than eating and drinking, right, bathing, sex, anointing and so on,
similar ambiguity. The גמרא Gemara learns it out from verses, makes it
sound like it's biblical. Of course it's not exactly clear how you
get those particular ones although there's a סוגיא sugya about that. And
then at the other hand you get overrides. What are the overrides
for the עינויים? inuyim? Like a כלה, kallah, right, a recently married
woman, a מלך, melech, a king, certain types of circumstances that we
can say that oh, well in that case, special case, we'll let
you bathe or we'll let you do certain things on יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. So that makes it sound like it's only rabbinic. Okay,
so again, it's not just that the rabbis figure out the parameters.
The fact that there are overrides raises questions to whether or not
this is really something that is biblical. So this is like the
basic question,
A what's its weight, what's its source, is it biblical, rabbinic, is
it somewhere in between, and B what exactly is the character of
the איסור מלאכה issur melacha on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Yes?
Doesn't it seem unreasonable to imagine that that the מלאכה melacha is
determined by the context rather than the kind of categorical definition, just
what we're kind of trained and accustomed to thinking in categories?
Okay, so what you're saying is, and this is something also that
is said by for example the כלה kallah washing the face on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, is that you have to view that as
an override or can you say in those circumstances it's not about
תענוג, ta'anug, it's the sort and it's about something else? Okay, so
it is possible, that's true, to re-characterize it.
You know again to say מלאכה melacha done to prevent the loss
is not real מלאכה. melacha. Okay, but maybe you'll define it, you
know what type of מלאכה melacha we're talking about? We're talking about
מלאכת הרווחה. melachas harvacha. We're not talking about מלאכת מניעת הפסד melachas
menias hefsed and it's part of the character of it rather than
an override. So that is possible, whether it'll always work, but that
is definitely a possible way to sort of find a path, not
frame it as an override, but frame it as giving it a
different character.
Yeah, but I'm still- I'm still tying my field regardless.
I understand, so what the משנה mishna is- if you don't think
in terms of ל"ט מלאכות, lamed tes melachos, right? If I said,
you know, don't go into work on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, right?
So, you know- I'm trying to think of an example- yeah, watch
TV. Okay, but you know- or you know, you shouldn't be working
on your computer on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Well, let's say I'm
reading a novel on my computer, or let's say, you know what
I'm saying? For- sometimes you have- if you're thinking not in terms
of like technical מלאכות melachos but more the purpose and the goals
of it, you know, and it's more about profession. And of course
this is also professional, but it's again maybe a different quality to
the מלאכה. melacha. It's definitely something to think about, okay? And you're
right, then we have to think in very different types of categories,
and that's an interesting thing about מלאכת חול המועד melechet Chol HaMoed
that they might not at all follow the normal type of ל"ט.
lamed tes. Other types of things you have are things like מלאכת
אומן, melechet uman, right? Is it craftsmanly labor or not craftsmanly labor,
right? So it could be the exact same in terms of a
שבת Shabbat category, but how much is it something that's skilled and
craftsman's labor as opposed to not? These are types of issues that
we will see. Let's keep on going, just putting all those things
on the table. Okay, so now it continues.
Okay, so משקין בית השלחין במועד ובשביעית. Mashkin beit hashalachin bamoed uvishvi'it.
On שמיטה Shmita as well? Now that should be a shocker, right?
Because if שמיטה Shmita you're not allowed to water your field, no-
that's a דאורייתא Deoraita taking- tending to your crops and whatever on
שמיטה. Shmita. And how does הפסד hefsed allow it? So that's going
to be a big issue.
בין ממעיין שיצא בתחילה בין ממעיין שלא
יצא בתחילה.
Bein mimayan sheyatza batchila
bein mimayan shelo yatza batchila.
Whether from a spring that has just originally emerged or whether one
that has not originally emerged. It's more obvious if it's not originally
emerged because that means that it is like, you know, it's sort
of- the- it's- the structure has been established, like the spring and
the furrow and all of that, and you're not afraid that it'll
collapse when you go ahead and use the water from it. Whereas
something that's new, you know, it might dry up, it might collapse,
and then it would lead to doing a lot of work. So
therefore you might not want to allow it because it might lead
to a lot of work. And nevertheless, it's allowed because this is
a מקום הפסד. makom hefsed. אבל אין משקין לא ממי גשמים. Aval
ein mashkin lo mimei geshamim.
You cannot use it from collected rainwater, which is a lot more
effort, right? So basically drawing it from like water that's collected in
these buckets. ולא ממי הקילון. Velo mimei hakilon.
And not from water from a like a pipe or a device
that was used to like raise water from the bottom of a
deep well. Those are things that are too effortful and טרחא tircha
and therefore not allowed.
Okay, so the collected rainwater you can't use?
Right, I mean we're not talking about like, I don't know, take
a little bit of water. We're talking about a whole effort of
like drawing water from a well, so that's like, you know, that
is- that is much more effortful and therefore that is not allowed.
ואין עושים... Ve'ein osim... again, I don't know enough about, you know,
agriculture in those realities, but we can sort of trust that there
was a huge difference in effort here. ואין עושים עוגיות לגפנים. Ve'ein
osim ugiot lagfanim. You cannot make furrows around the- around the vines,
because digging furrows so that when the water falls it collects and
it stays in that place and continues to nurture the vines... presumably
again, the question we have to ask is what we see implicit
in the beginning of the משנה mishna is you're allowed to do
things
when it's במקום הפסד, bemakom hefsed, but not if it's too much
טרחא. tircha. So for example, not allowing עוגיות לגפנים, ugiot lagfanim, is
that because it's not considered הפסד? hefsed? More logically, it is because
it would be too much טרחא tircha digging- digging those things. So
you- it's- טרחא? tircha? Right, exactly. And some wanted to say that
חוני המעגל Choni HaMa'agel was not because of the circle he drew,
was because he worked- he dug ditches by- by vines, and therefore
he was very sensitive to the need of rain. Okay, רבי אליעזר
בן עזריה אומר... Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah omer... anyway, these are the
two criteria: it has to be מקום הפסד makom hefsed and it
can't be too much טרחא. tircha. רבי אליעזר בן עזריה אומר
אין עושים את האמה בתחילה במועד ובשביעית. Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah omer
ein osim et ha'amah batchila bamoed uvishvi'it. You
cannot initially
make a- a furrow to- you know, to run water through... irrigation
canal, thank you. What were you saying, Jon? Irrigation ditch. Yeah, irrigation
ditch, thank you. You cannot do an irrigation ditch initially on- on
חול המועד- Chol HaMoed, I'm sorry, yeah, on חול המועד Chol HaMoed
and on שביעית. Shvi'it. Again, presumably because even if it's הפסד, hefsed,
it's considered too much טרחא. tircha. וחכמים אומרים עושים את האמה בתחילה
בשביעית. Vachachamim omrim osim et ha'amah batchila bishvi'it. You are allowed to
do it on שביעית Shvi'it initially, this irrigation ditch. ומתקנים את המקולקלות
במועד. Umetaknin et hamukalkalot bamoed. And if- you can't make it initially
on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed. but if it got- if it sort
of collapsed and is, you know, and you need to clean it
out and- you know, and sort of re-strengthen it and fix it,
that you are allowed to do. Now that's fascinating, because I think
most of us would have assumed that we- should be shocked that
you can do any of this
on שביעית Shvi'it and
we- That's
what—oh no, of course you can fix it. You can only
even on שמיטה Shmita you can even make it לכתחילה. lichatchila. On
חול המועד Chol HaMoed you can you can only fix it. ומתקנים
את קלקולי המים שברשות הרבים, U'metaknim et kilkulei hamayim shebi'reshut harabim, the
same way you can fix these irrigation canals, you can also fix
other types of things that are used for, you know, sort of
conveying water that have that have collapsed or that need are in
disrepair in the public domain, or for collecting water, let's say, you
know, it's for the masses to to drink from, you know, you
have certain wells and whatever, that you're allowed to do. וחוטטין אותן
V'chotetin otan and again you can sort of dig them not initially
make them but you can dig them out if like dirt has
fell into it, it's collapsed. Okay, that you can do. Now here
we are introduced to presumably a third
allowance which is צרכי רבים, tzorchei rabim, right? So now we're not
dealing with getting your your fields irrigated, we're having the masses have
availability of water, so we're dealing with צרכי רבים tzorchei rabim and
that is allowed. Okay, and
somewhat seems to be on a similar plane as the case of
הפסד hefsed by the חול המועד. Chol HaMoed, חול המועד Chol HaMoed
you can fix things, irrigation canals that are מקולקלות, mekukalot, and these
צרכי רבים, tzorchei rabim, these wells and other things, you can fix
if they are מקולקלות, mekukalot, presumably you cannot dig new ones. Okay.
So, ומתקנים את הדרכים והרחובות ואת מקואות המים. u'metaknim et haderachim v'ha-rechovot
v'et mikva'ot hamayim.
You can similarly fix the, you know, the roads and the streets
and the
מקואות. mikva'ot. ועושין כל צרכי הרבים V'osin kol tzorchei harabim and here
it just gives you the principle all needs of the masses. ומציינין
את הקברות U'metzayinin et hakevarot you can designate the graves so the
כהנים Kohanim know to avoid them. ויוצאין אף על הכלאים V'yotzin af
al hakilayim and you send out the שליחי בית דין shlichei beit
din in order to supervise make sure that people are not growing
כלאים. kilayim. Right. And so yeah, okay. So we'll hear about all
of that. But anyway, at the end you have a whole collection
of things that are צרכי רבים tzorchei rabim and again, questions to
ask is how much is there an issue here? Are there cases
where this would be too much טרחה tircha and not allowed? Or
does this does this also have the issue of טרחה tircha or
not the issue of טרחה? tircha? But by your own private field
on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, the issue you have is if it's
מקום הפסד makom hefsed and if it's not going to be excessive
טרחה. tircha. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. השתא Hashta
says גמרא Gemara יש לומר ממים שיצאו בתחילה דאתי לאינפולי yesh lomar
mimayim sheyatza bat'chila d'ati l'inpulei
if so fascinating which מסכת masechet begin by asking broad questions like
מנא הני מילי, minani milei, like where's this whole idea about not
doing מלאכה melacha on חול המועד Chol HaMoed, or something? No, here
we start with a very narrow question. Like we take everything for
granted and we just want to know
whether a new well or not a new well, okay, so
or spring. השתא יש לומר ממים שיצאו בתחילה דאתי
לאינפולי משקין Hashta yesh lomar mimayim sheyatza bat'chila d'ati l'inpulei mashkin if
you can irrigate from a well that has that is brand new
and that has more of a likelihood of, you know, of needing
repair because it hasn't sort of like, you know, sort of gotten
like the the walls and the the structure and all that, ay
yai yai there, are not, you know, have not sort of become
deeply dug and established. So in that case you're allowed to do
it. ממים שלא יצאו בתחילה דלא אתי לאינפולי Mimayim shelo yatza bat'chila
d'lo ati l'inpulei
a well that has not just recently emerged that we're not afraid
that the the banks will fall fall in, so מיבעיא mibaya is
there any question? Of course you can do that. So of course,
you know, the גמרא Gemara could have given the standard answer like
a זו אין צריך לומר זו zu ein tzarich lomar zu type
of a thing, but let's see what the גמרא Gemara does answer.
אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Papa no, איצטריך Itzterich you need to
say both. אי תנא מים שיצאו בתחילה Ee tana mayim sheyatza bat'chila
if it said you can do it from a spring that has
just emerged which is a bigger חידוש, chiddush, you were not afraid
that it'll collapse and you'll have to do all the effort of
redigging it. הוה אמינא Hava amina I would have said הכא הוא
דבית השלחין לבית
הבעל. hacha hu d'beit hashlachin l'beit habaal. Here's where we make this
distinction between a field that needs irrigation and a בית הבעל beit
habaal which we'll explain what that word means, what the etymology is,
but basically means a field that does not need irrigation, that's fine
with rainwater. So that's why we're going to make a distinction because
we're dealing with a precarious type of a of a of a
spring, of a well, of a spring. משום דאתי לאינפולי Mishum d'ati
l'inpulei we're afraid the walls might collapse. הבעל Abaal I would have
thought if it's a מים שלא יצאו בתחילה mayim shelo yatza bat'chila
if it's a spring that has not recently emerged, that it's well
established, דלא אתי לאינפולי d'lo ati l'inpulei there's no concern of collapse,
in that type of a case הוה אמינא Hava amina I might
have thought אפילו בית הבעל נמי, afilu beit habaal nami, if we're
not concerned of it collapsing and there's not so much effort, maybe
I should allow it even in something that survives on rainwater, that
doesn't really need the water so much, isn't a הפסד, hefsed, maybe
even though it's not a הפסד hefsed issue, I would still allow
it because there's very little concern. So קא משמע לן לא שנא
מים שיצאו בתחילה לא שנא מים שלא יצאו בתחילה Kamashmalan lo shna
mayim sheyatza bat'chila lo shna mayim shelo yatza bat'chila doesn't matter if
it's a new one, doesn't matter if it's an old one, בית
השלחין אין beit hashlachin in only a field that needs irrigation do
we have an
allowance, בית הבעל. beit habaal. So therefore, rule number one is that
the only allowance is מקום הפסד. makom hefsed. If it's not מקום
הפסד, makom hefsed, if it's an issue not of הפסד hefsed but
of the other phrase again about הפסד hefsed is מניעת רווח, meniat
revach, right? So there's a difference: is it about losing money or
is it about not making a profit? Now, it's actually interesting, and
I'm not going to get into this discussion, I just want to
footnote it, that what do you deal with nowadays if somebody says
like if I don't go into work on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed
right, they're going to, I don't know, cut my salary, or I'll
have to use up one of my, you know, sick days or
something like that. So is that like מניעת רווח, meniat revach, like
you're just not getting extra money? Let's not do the sick day
case. So I'll have to give up my salary for that day,
right? Is that מניעת רווח meniat revach or do you say look,
if you start the year assuming I'm earning a salary of X
amount, and I'm going to have to take a cut in salary,
so on one hand I'm not earning money for that day, on
the other hand I'm sort of losing, you know, my income. So
how exactly, you know, do we always draw the line between those
two is not always clear, but those are the issues. So the
גמרא Gemara says if it's a בית הבעל beit haba'al if it's
something that needs irrigation without which the crops are going to be
damaged, that is a case of הפסד, hefsed, you'll lose the crops.
Okay, you don't say like wow, no crops will grow, that's just
no רווח. revach. No, like if you don't have crops growing, that's
a הפסד. hefsed. However, if it's something that really doesn't really need
it, it can be fine with the rainwater, it's just making the
crops better, that's an issue of רווח, revach, מניעת רווח, meniat revach,
and that's a case where there's no allowance. So the משנה Mishnah
is saying whether it's a, you know, whatever the case is in
terms of the wellspring, the allowance is only going to be for
an issue of בית השלחין, beit hashalchin, for a case of הפסד.
hefsed. It's not going to be for a בית הבעל beit haba'al
where there's an issue of רווח, revach, there there is no allowance.
Now the גמרא Gemara gets to the different
etymologies—these are חול המועד, Chol HaMoed. we're not dealing with שמיטה Shmita
yet. Let's deal now with the etymology of these words:
ומאי משמע דהאי בית השלחין לישנא דצחותא היא? u'mai mashma de'hai beit
hashalchin lishna detzachuta hi? Where does this idea of בית השלחין—you beit
hashalchin get the idea that it means a language of
thirst? דכתיב, dechtiv, the verse
says: ואתה עיף ויגיע—and ve'ata ayef ve'yageya you were weary, and you
were weary and tired and
weary—ומתרגמינן, u'metargeminin, the תרגום Targum is: ואת משלהי ולאי—and ve'at mishalhei ve'la'i
you were thirsty and weary. So משלהי mishalhei is reading to read...
משלהי mishalhei is thirsty, and they're playing on a dual play on
words, משלהי mishalhei and השלחין. hashalchin. The ה hei and the ח
chet are switching. Now that's probably...
thirsty? Yeah. So there...
I mean, תרגום Targum probably also means I think, I don't know,
you can check it. I think that actually Aramaic probably even more
also means weary than it does thirsty.
But that's how Steinzaltz translates it.
Weary and tired? Weary. So it's like faint and weary. So it's
a little like of a double, you know, two degrees removed: weary
meaning thirsty, and משלהי mishalhei meaning השלחין. hashalchin. So it's really not
the real etymology. I did look up what the etymology is, but
I would imagine it would have to do with the word לשלוח
lishloach because what you're doing is you're conveying water to the field,
right? You're irrigating the field.
So I don't know
if Steinzaltz provides it so to speak with the weariness.
Maybe. Anyway, but I just don't know if... does Steinzaltz give the
etymology, the real etymology of בית השלחין? beit hashalchin?
I imagine it has to do with conveying for the water to
the field.
וישלח מים על פני חוצות.
veyishlach mayim
al pnei chutzot. Right, exactly, exactly. So anyway, let's keep on going.
So that's what it says, is where that means a field that
is thirsty, that is in need of water. Okay, now ומאי משמע
דהאי בית הבעל לישנא דמיסופתא דמיאשותא היא? u'mai mashma de'hai beit haba'al
lishna demiysufta de'miasuta hi? How do you know the language of בית
הבעל beit haba'al means settled? Whoever said it meant settled? But okay,
you know, sated and settled, דכתיב, dechtiv, which is the opposite of
thirsty, דכתיב כי יבעל בחור בתולה—as dechtiv ki yival bachur betulah a
young man will, you know, have sex with a with a young
woman—ומתרגמינן: u'metargeminin: ארי כמה דמיתסות עולם עם בתולתא—like arei kama demityasot ulam
im betulta a young man will be settled with a virgin. יתיבותא...
Yetivuta... and that fits the end of the verse because it's a,
you know, it's a metaphor for בני ישראל: Bnei Yisrael: ייתיבון בגויך
בניך—your yityivun begavayich banayich children will be settled in you, in the
land of Israel. So that's what it says: בית הבעל beit haba'al
is the opposite of thirsty, is a land that is sated, that
does not really need regular water, and therefore there is no issue
of הפסד. hefsed. Now, by the way, the probably there the etymology
seems clearer,
right, because the whole idea, I think we discussed this a little
bit in תענית, Ta'anit, but the whole idea that rain, you know,
comes down and it penetrates the earth, and then it's, you know,
fertilizes the, you know, seed in the ground, and up from it
sprouts crops, right, is very sexual in that imagery, right? And it's
mother earth and it's being penetrated. And you actually have that in
the... what is it, in the הפטרה Haftarah that we read by
תענית? Ta'anit? What is it? What's the פסוק pasuk about כי כאשר...
לא, ירד הגשם והשלג מן השמים ושמה לא ישוב? ki ka'asher... lo,
yered hageshem vehashelag min hashamayim veshama lo yashuv? No,
that's not exactly, but still, that's more like just rain coming from
God. But what? והולידה והצמיחה, veholida vehitzmicha, right. So you know, it
comes from God, it comes, penetrates, it gives birth, and whatever. And
that's also the idea of rain and God and the, you know,
which ties into the whole issues of תענית. Ta'anit. So the בית
הבעל beit haba'al is something that actually is survives on the rainwater,
right, and it's all and it's all playing off of that imagery.
Now, that's what I had always thought, and then last night I
checked the footnotes in Soncino and again I cannot, you know, I'm
not attesting to this or whatever, but whoever was that wrote that,
you know, who did that, points to some scholarly discussion that it
actually refers to the pagan god בעל Baal and because these fields
were so fertile, so they were fields that were favored by בעל.
Baal. Okay, and that might have to do with that, I'm sure
that also plays into the same imagery though about, you know, you
know, about the whatever role that pagan god had or whatever. But
surprisingly, that's not in the גמרא. Gemara. So, okay. So anyway, let's
keep on going.
Okay. So anyway, so only for fields that really need the water
and that it's a real הפסד. hefsed. Okay.
מאן תנא דפסידא אין והרווחה לא? Man tana d'pseda in v'harvacha lo?
Now we're getting to the core principles here, to the criteria.
Who is the one that says that you're only allowed to do
things on חול המועד chol hamoed. if there's a real פסידא, pseda,
not for the sake of profit but for preventing loss? And there's
two criteria,
remember, דאפילו במקום פסידא טירחא נמי לא שרינן, d'afilu b'makom pseda, tircha
nami lo sharinan, we don't allow it with טירחא tircha because we
don't allow rainwater, we only allow, you know, these wells that have
already been established and so on. We don't allow things that might
lead to טירחא tircha or that involve טירחא. tircha.
So רש"י Rashi says דאטרחו בחול המועד d'itrachu b'Chol HaMoed means like
a little bit of טירחא, tircha, right? No, it says itself טירחא,
tircha, טירחא לא ליטרחו בחול המועד. tircha lo litrachu b'Chol HaMoed.
Yes, right, so there's always a question of degree of טירחא, tircha,
correct. So that's also a question of how exactly you draw the
line. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, so says רב הונא, Rav
Huna, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב היא. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov hi. It's
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, דתניא במשנה, d'tanya b'mishna,
we learned in the משנה, mishna, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר: Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov omer: מושכין את המים מאילן לאילן ובלבד שלא ישקה
את השדה כולה. moshchin et hamayim me'ilan l'ilan u'bilvad shelo yashke et
hasadeh kullah. That you can draw water from one tree to another,
so water has collected around one tree, you can like make a
furrow to have it go from one tree and to go to
another tree. And it's assumed here that the issues around the trees
are like the בית השלחין, beit hashalchin, our cases where that actually
is a case of a הפסד, hefsed, that you can do, but
you cannot have it go, you know, draw it from the tree
and have it water the rest of the field. So the גמרא
Gemara assumes that that would be because, you could say it's a
טירחא tircha issue, but the גמרא Gemara assumes it's because the rest
of the field is a הרווחה harvacha issue. So you see that
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov does not allow you
to do something for הרווחה. harvacha. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, אימא דשמען ליה לרבי אליעזר, eima d'shaman lei l'Rabbi Eliezer, when
did רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say his
position? הרווחה דלא. Harvacha d'lo. That you're not allowed to do things
that are for הרווחה. harvacha. That's fine, you can only do things
for הפסד. hefsed. But we have a second criteria we have to
address. טירחא במקום פסידא מי שמען ליה? Tircha b'makom pseda mi shaman
lei? But when did you ever hear any position that if it's
a פסידא, pseda, that even in a case of פסידא, pseda, you
can't do it if it's a טירחא? tircha? That we don't know.
We know he doesn't want you to do הרווחה, harvacha, but where
do we know our second criteria that even in a case of
פסידא, pseda, if it's טירחא tircha it's no good? אלא אמר רב
פפא, Ella amar Rav Papa, הא מני? ha mani? רבי יהודה היא.
Rabbi Yehuda hi. It's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דתניא, De-tanya, we learned
in a ברייתא, baraita, מעיין היוצא בתחילה, ma'ayan hayotze batchila, so here
is the ברייתא baraita that presumably is the backstory to the משנה,
mishna, a wider range of positions around the issue in the משנה.
mishna. מעיין היוצא בתחילה משקין ממנו אפילו שדה בית הבעל, Ma'ayan hayotze
batchila, mashkin mimeno afilu sadeh beit haba'al, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi
Meir. If you have even a brand new well, a brand new
spring, you can irrigate with it even a בית הבעל, beit haba'al,
דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is
very lenient. It's a new spring, so you could be concerned that
the walls will collapse or whatever, we're not concerned about that. And
you can use it for a בית הבעל, beit haba'al, you can
use it even not for פסידא, pseda, even if it's just for
הרווחה. harvacha. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir very lenient. דברי רבי מאיר.
Divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda who is now the גמרא Gemara is saying is the author
of our משנה, mishna, אין משקין אלא שדה בית השלחין שחרבה. ein
mashkin ella sadeh beit hashalchin shecharva. You can only do it for
a field that requires irrigation that has dried, that is in need
of irrigation, so just like our משנה. mishna. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה
אומר: Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya omer: לא כך ולא כך. lo kach
v'lo kach. Now רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya is
the most extreme, even a dried up field that needs irrigation you
cannot do. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is the middle position.
יתר כן אמר רבי יהודה, Yeter ken amar Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda went even further and said: לא יפנה אדם אמת המים
וישקה לגינתו ולחורבתו בחול המועד. lo yifaneh adam ammat hamayim v'yashke l'ginato
u'l'chorvato b'Chol HaMoed. You cannot redirect a irrigation canal and have it,
you know, and have it water your garden or your, you know,
your yard on חול המועד. Okay, so what?
חורבה Chorva means your yard?
Right. So רש"י... Rashi... okay so that is now if you take
a look, תוספות Tosafot says what these two things are, גינתו וחורבתו,
ginato v'chorvato, תוספות Tosafot says: של בית השלחין. shel beit hashalchin. So
number one, those are things that are הפסד, hefsed, they are in
need of water. גינה מקום זרעים חורבה מקום שחרבו אילנותיו וחשיב וזרע
ונטע. Gina makom zera'im, chorba makom she-charvu ilanosav v'chashiv v'zara v'nata. Okay,
so it's basically a field that's in the process of being replanted,
ושמא צריך למים יותר, v'shemo tzarich le-mayim yoter, and he goes on
and so on. Okay, so anyway so there is so what we
see is two things, so anyway so let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. So the
גמרא Gemara says: מאי חורבה? mai chorva? What does it mean a
irrigated field
that
has dried
up?
אילימא
חורבה.
Ileima
chorva.
Right. So wait, if before we get to רבי אלעזר בן עזריה,
Rabbi Eliezer ben Azariah, let’s just take a stop and explain what
we know by
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So רבי יהודה’s Rabbi Yehuda telling us, so
from here רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda we see that רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda is the author of our משנה mishna in two ways. Number
one is that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that you can go
ahead and you can, if the wellspring has dried up, you can
go ahead and, you know, and irrigate it from this מעיין. ma’ayan.
So that would tell you that’s because it’s a פסידא, p’seida, you’re
allowed to irrigate it, right, because the wellspring has dried up. Let’s
take a look at רבינו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, he spells it out.
So take a look here, it’s about eight lines before the lines
get wide. He says, שחרבה ממעיין זה ויצא לה מעיין אחר. shecharva
mima’ayan zeh veyatza la ma’ayan acher. שחרבה מעיינה שרגיל לשתות ממנו, shecharva
mayana she-ragil lishtos mimenu, דכיון שרגיל לשתות, de-keivan she-ragil lishtos,
this was the wellspring dried up and now it’s, you know, and
so now it normally was reliant on it. So אי לא משקא
לה עכשיו אית לה פסידא יתירא. ilo mashka le-achshav isla p'seida yeseira.
If you don't continue to do it now, there's going to be
a פסידא. p'seida. אפילו הכא, afilu hacha, and even though we're clearly
talking about a case of פסידא, p'seida, so number one is you
see that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is allowing it only because it
is בית השלחין וחרבה, Beis HaShalkhin ve-charva, so only not for רווח,
revach, like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir allowed it for רווח, revach, בית
הבעל. Beis HaBa'al. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda only allows בית השלחין, Beis
HaShalkhin, so it's הפסד hefsed and חרבה, charva, that's number one, only
הפסד. hefsed. Now how do you see the טרחא tircha aspect? So
let's take a look that that's also a criteria. So רבינו גרשום
Rabbeinu Gershom here continues, one minute, ואפילו הכא לא שרי רבי יהודה
אלא ממעיין שיצא לה. ve-afilu hacha lo shari Rabbi Yehuda ela mima'ayan
she-yatza la. And even so, right, what's the case of the ברייתא?
braisa? מעיין היוצא בתחילה mayan ha-yotzei bas-chila only from a מעיין. mayan.
דלאו טרחא הוא, delav tircha hu, you're only allowed to do it
from a מעיין, mayan, אבל מי גשמים ומי קילון דטרחא הוא לא
שרי אפילו בית השלחין. aval mei geshamim u-mei kilun de-tircha hu, lo
shari afilu Beis HaShalkhin. So basically we see רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
is in our משנה mishna because it has the same criteria as
our משנה. mishna. A, we're talking about a בית השלחין, Beis HaShalkhin,
that's the only case רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allows, and B, we're
talking about a מעיין mayan like our משנה. mishna. So the implication
being that if it was more effort like well water or rain
water, it would not be allowed. And we also see it from
the second statement of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. ועוד חזינא דקאמר רבי
יהודה לא יפנה אדם, ve-od chazina de-ka'amar Rabbi Yehuda lo yifaneh adam,
you cannot redirect the אמה, amah, the irrigation
canal. אלמא דלא שרי רבי יהודה טרחא יתירא. almah delo shari Rabbi
Yehuda tircha yeseira. Now why not? As תוספות Tosafos just told us,
בגינה וחורבה bagina ve-chorva are cases of בית השלחין, Beis HaShalkhin, are
cases of הפסד, hefsed, and he doesn't allow you to redirect it.
So you see that even with הפסד, hefsed, טרחא tircha is not
allowed. אלמא מתניתין רבי יהודה היא. almah matnitin Rabbi Yehuda hi. Okay,
because רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Eliezer ben Azariah is clearly much
more מחמיר. machmir. All right, so is that clear,
or maybe I should write some of this down? Yeah, maybe helpful.
So
we have the ברייתא braisa that basically sets a case of a
מעיין. mayan. Okay, that's the case of the ברייתא. braisa. מעיין שיצא
בתחילה, mayan she-yatza bas-chila, but we are not going to worry right
now about the בתחילה, bas-chila, we have the case of a מעיין.
mayan. Okay, which means no טרחא, tircha, no, but whatever, no significant
טרחא. tircha. Okay, so what's the position? So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says בעל, ba'al, בית הבעל, Beis HaBa'al, right, stay בעל. ba'al. So
basically according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you can do it even,
you know, even for רווח. revach. רבי אלעזר
בן עזריה
Rabbi Eliezer ben
Azariah says לא זה ולא זה, lo zeh velo zeh, neither, right,
so no, even for הפסד. hefsed.
Okay, now comes along רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and he says you
can do it for what? For a בית השלחין, Beis HaShalkhin, right,
which means you can do it for הפסד. hefsed. Okay, that's what
it's allowed. So that tells us one point, you're allowed to do
it for הפסד. hefsed. But this in מעיין, ma'ayan, that's criteria number
one, hefsed. But the fact that it's dealing with a מעיין mayan
says you need it both for only for הפסד hefsed and if
there's no טרחא. tircha. If it would have to be drawing it
from a well or rain water, it would be no good. And
then we have the other statement of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda which
says you cannot what? You can't be direct the אמה, amah,
the
like the canal for your... for your גינה gina and חורבה. churba.
Now the assumption here is, as we just read in תוספות, Tosafot,
that that's like a בית השלחין. Beit HaShalchin. Okay? That that's a
case of הפסד. hefsed. Why can you not redirect it? You cannot,
you cannot, you
cannot
redirect. Why can you not redirect it if it's a הפסד? hefsed?
It must be that the redirecting is again an issue of טרחא.
tircha. So you see that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda has two issues.
It has to be הפסד, hefsed, it has to be a בית
השלחין Beit HaShalchin and for גינה gina and חורבה, churba, and only
if there's no טרחא. tircha.
If it's a מעיין, ma'ayan, if it needs redirecting the אמה, amah,
that will not be allowed.
Okay? So those are the issues. Let's take a look.
So now we'll pick up see רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi Elazar
ben Azaria, three lines up from the bottom. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה
אומר Rabbi Elazar ben Azaria omer לא כך ולא כך, lo kach
velo kach, neither this nor that, nothing is allowed. לא שנא חרב
מעיינו ולא שנא לא חרב מעיינו, lo shena charav mayano velo shena
lo charav mayano, I don't care if the well has dried up
then it's a הפסד hefsed issue. מעיין שיצא בתחילה לא ישקי, mayan
sheyatza batchila lo yashki, you cannot do it from a wellspring, a
new wellspring. Now maybe he would allow an old wellspring, maybe he's
just saying a new one, I'm afraid it's going to collapse. So
the גמרא Gemara says
וממאי, u-mmai, how do you know that that's רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda?
דדילמא, di-dilma,
maybe עד כאן לא קאמר רבי יהודה בית השלחין אין בית הבעל
לא? ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Yehuda Beit HaShalchin in, Beit HaBa'al
lo? Maybe רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda only makes a difference between בית
השלחין Beit HaShalchin and בית הבעל, Beit HaBa'al, אלא מעיין שיצא בתחילה,
ella mayan sheyatza batchila, so only because it's a new wellspring. Maybe
he's limiting here and he's limiting to the case of הפסד, hefsed,
since he's afraid this well will collapse. But if it's not new,
if it's old, maybe he would be very liberal and he'd allow
you to do even a בית הבעל. Beit HaBa'al. So how do
you know that he's exactly our משנה? Mishnah? Our משנה Mishnah doesn't
distinguish between the type of מעיין. mayan. So דילמא אתי לאינתפולי dilma
atei l'intfulei because he's afraid it'll collapse, אבל מעיין שלא יצא בתחילה,
aval mayan shelo yatza batchila, maybe if it's an old מעיין, mayan,
דלא אתי לאינתפולי, d'lo atei l'intfulei, it won't collapse, אפילו בית הבעל
נמי, afilu Beit HaBa'al nami, maybe he would allow you even if
it's not הפסד. hefsed. Right? So he's not exactly our משנה, Mishnah,
he doesn't address that case. So the גמרא Gemara says no. אם
כן מתניתין דמאן, im ken matnitin d'man, whoever else are you going
to attribute the משנה Mishnah to? Meaning it's 90% overlap to the
משנה. Mishnah. So he doesn't address the question of what if it's
an old wellspring. Is he hypothetically in a different position? Yeah, but
we don't find anybody else that the משנה Mishnah matches up with
except רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So we're going to assume that our
משנה Mishnah is רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: אלא רבי יהודה לא שנא מעיין שיצא בתחילה
ולא שנא מעיין שלא יצא בתחילה, ella Rabbi Yehuda lo shena mayan
sheyatza batchila velo shena mayan shelo yatza batchila, although in the ברייתא
Beraita he's only talking about a new well, we can assume that
whether a new well or an old, you know, spring, בית השלחין
אין בית הבעל לא. Beit HaShalchin in, Beit HaBa'al lo. He will
only allow בית השלחין Beit HaShalchin because it's הפסד. hefsed. He only
allowed מקום הפסד, makom hefsed, לא במקום רווח, lo bemakom revach, and
even there only when there is no טרחא. tircha. והא דקתני מעיין
שיצא בתחילה, veha diktani mayan sheyatza batchila, so then why does the
ברייתא Beraita talk about a new well? If רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
would allow a בית השלחין Beit HaShalchin even with a, excuse me,
if he would limit his היתר heter to a case of הפסד
hefsed whether it was new or old, why are we talking only
about a new well? להודיע כוחו דרבי מאיר, l'odeia kocho de-Rabbi Meir,
to tell you how powerful the היתר heter of רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir is, דאפילו מעיין היוצא בתחילה, de-afilu mayan hayotze batchila, even if
it's a brand new well and there's a concern it'll collapse, משקי
ממנו אפילו שדי הבעל, mashki mimenu afilu sdei haba'al, he would allow
you even to do a field that does not need irrigation. So
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is very lenient. He allows even for רווח
revach even though there's a concern that it might collapse, whereas רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allows only for הפסד. hefsed. Now when it is
a
הפסד, hefsed, he
will allow it
even though it might collapse as well, but only in case of
הפסד. hefsed. But רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, he will go so far
that even if it's a case of רווח revach where you might
have thought you want to limit the type of wellspring, רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir would allow even a brand new well. Okay?
So even for רווח, revach, even with טרחא, tircha, he would allow.
Exactly. Well, possible טרחא, tircha, right? It's not clear that רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir would allow you like draw water from collected rainwater. This
is a case where it might become possible טרחא, tircha, but it's
not right now possible טרחא. tircha. Okay. But it is true that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would not, if it was an old wellspring,
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would not give you more of a היתר.
heter. Okay. But we're talking about this case not to suggest that
there would be more היתרים heterim in the other case, but to
tell you the חידוש chiddush that even in this case רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir is very lenient. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara
continues. אתמר. itmar. Now we get onto, that's working out our משנה
Mishnah and we basically get as we said to those two criteria
about מקום הפסד makom hefsed and what do you call it, and
no טרחא, tircha, or no,
okay. Now, but we do allow a new wellspring even though there
might be טרחא, tircha, that's not going to bother us. That we'll
allow. But not if there's definite טרחא. tircha. אתמר, itmar, it was
taught: המנכש והמשקה מים לזרעים בשבת. ha-menakesh ve-hamashke mayim lizraim be-shabbat.
If somebody is going in, you know,
weeding or watering the
seeds on שבת shabbat that are in the ground or weeding the
area. So what you're doing is you're doing things that are encouraging
and fostering the growth of the seeds that have been planted. What
type of a מלאכה melacha is that? We'll see how this will
circle back to be relevant. So משום מאי מתרינן ביה? mishum mai
matrinan beih? What התראה hatra'ah warning do we give the person if
we want to, you know, give them punishment in a בית דין?
beit din? You have to warn them. Now there's an interesting debate
in the ראשונים rishonim when the גמרא gemara asks these questions of
משום מאי מתרינן ביה, mishum mai matrinan beih, if you just said,
don't do that, it's a מלאכה melacha on שבת, shabbat, would that
be sufficient התראה? hatra'ah? And he said, I don't care, I'm doing
it anyway, and he did it, would we be able to execute
him? So some say no, it's too generic, he doesn't really believe
you. Some say well, maybe that would be good. But let's say
you didn't give a generic התראה. hatra'ah. Let's say you gave a
specific התראה hatra'ah and you said, this is מלאכה melacha X on
שבת. shabbat. So there, if you give the wrong identification, then he
can clearly say, I was... that was a joke, that wasn't what
it was, and I didn't take him seriously. Okay, but the assumption,
the simple assumption of this גמרא gemara is it's not enough to
generically say it's a מלאכה, melacha, you have to be specific, but
at least we can say if you are being specific, you have
to be correct in your specificity. And this is the way the
גמרא gemara analyzes by saying what התראה hatra'ah do we give him
is another way of saying which of the thirty-nine מלאכה melacha categories
does it fall into? Okay, so what type of התראה hatra'ah would
you give such a person? רבה Rabbah אמר amar משום חורש. mishum
choresh. It's חורש choresh because what's חורש? choresh? חורש choresh is plowing.
Now, normally חורש choresh takes place before you put the seed in,
although there is a type of a חורש choresh that takes place
after the seed is already there. And חורש choresh is a working
of the ground that encourages the growth, that enables the growth of
what's planted. Well, that's what's happening here. You're either weeding it or
watering it, so you're doing something to the ground. The water doesn't
go straight to the seed, the water is absorbed by the dirt
and from the dirt the seed draws its nutrients. So you're doing
something to the ground that's helping the growth of the seed. It's
חורש. choresh. רב יוסף Rav Yosef אמר amar משום זורע. mishum zorea.
It's planting. Planting is about the growth of the seed. So this
thing is also... it's not done physically to the seed, but it's
about the growth of the seed and therefore it's planting. So אמר
רבה, amar Rabbah, so said רבה, Rabbah, כוותי דידי מסתברא, kevati didi
mistabra, like me makes sense. מה דרכא דחורש לרפויי ארעא, mah darcha
dechoresh lerapuyei ar'a, the same way חורש choresh sort of, you know,
softens the ground, improves the ground, האי נמי מרפויי ארעא, hai nami
marpuyei ar'a, this also improves the ground, softens and improves the ground
for purposes of planting. אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, no, כוותי
דידי מסתברא, kevati didi mistabra, like me makes sense. מה דרכא דזורע
לצמוחי פירא, mah darcha dezorea letsmuchi peira, the idea of planting is
to cause fruit to grow, to blossom, הכא נמי מצמח פירא, hacha
nami matsmach peira, this also causes the fruit to grow. So that's
what it's about. Now, what is... how could we conceptualize what they're
really arguing about? So תוספות Tosafot says what they're arguing about is
how much when you have to categorize a מלאכה, melacha, do you
want to put it in the category that's most similar to it
in terms of the physical activity or most similar to it in
terms of the purpose and the function? Because a תולדה toladah could
be either. I'll give you an example, right? One תולדה toladah of
cooking would be baking. Okay, baking doesn't look like cooking, right? I
mean, okay, but it's, you know, or frying or whatever. I mean,
there are certain similarities. But basically, it's... another תולדה toladah of cooking
is heating up a piece of metal and softening it to use
it, you know, to mold it, to shape it or whatever. That's...
that's not the same purpose as cooking, but it's similar in terms
of the idea of putting something over a fire, changing its form
and so on. Okay, so there are times in which, I'll give
you other examples, there are times in which מלאכה melacha sometimes is
similar in terms of purpose and sometimes is similar in terms of
form. And therefore this seems to be the question: if you have
to choose between which of those two categories to put it in,
which one would you put it in? Okay, take a quick look
at תוספות Tosafot who says this. He says כמרפויי ארעא, kemarpuyei ar'a,
תוספות Tosafot says בתר עיקר מלאכה אזלינן, batar ikkar melacha azlinan, דדמי
לחורש. dedami lechoresh.
He calls that עיקר מלאכה, ikkar melacha, but he says the form
of the מלאכה. melacha. ורב יוסף אף על גב דעיקר מלאכה דמי
לחורש, veRav Yosef af al gav deikkar melacha dami lechoresh, although it's
working the ground in a manner similar to חורש, choresh, מחשבת הנפש,
machshevet hanefesh,
interestingly he phrased it, לאו לרפויי ארעא. lav lerapuyei ar'a. That's not
the goal of it. You're not trying to improve the ground, you're
trying to grow the fruit. ובהכי פליגי דראבא סבר לבטר המעשה מדמינן
ליה, ubehachi peligi deRabba savar lebatar hama'aseh medaminan leih, this is a
clearer explication of it, you go by the physical act, ולא אחר
מחשבה, velo achar machshavah, not by your intent or the goal, ורב
יוסף סבר בתר מחשבה אזלינן דהוי עיקר ולא אזלינן בתר הדמיון. veRav
Yosef savar batar machshavah azlinan dehavei ikkar velo azlinan batar hadimyon. Okay,
דמיון dimyon means comparison, not דמיון dimyon like לדמות ledamot to imagine,
but by how it's physically comparable to. Okay, so that's the debate.
So let's get back to the גמרא. gemara. Okay, so אמר ליה
אביי לרבה. amar leih Abaye leRabba. אביי Abaye said
to רבה Rabbah who said it was חורש. choresh. לדידך קשיא ולרב
יוסף קשיא. ledidach kashya uleRav Yosef kashya. I got a problem according
to you and I got a problem according to רב יוסף. Rav
Yosef. לדידך קשיא, ledidach kashya, for you I have a problem, משום
חורש אין משום זורע לא? mishum choresh in mishum zorea lo? Okay,
I get why it's חורש. choresh. But isn't it also זורע? zorea?
לרב יוסף קשיא. leRav Yosef kashya. I have a problem for רב
יוסף. Rav Yosef. משום זורע אין משום חורש לא? mishum zorea in
mishum choresh lo?
Why is it only זורע? zorea? Why isn't it also חורש? choresh?
Of course, something could only be... I mean, it's not two different
things that are taking place in the same act. It's one act,
so you can't double categorize, you've got to choose. וכי תימא כל
היכא דאיכא תרתי לא מחייב אלא חדא, vechi teima kol heicha deika
tarti lo mechayiv ella chada, if you want to tell me if
you've got two things going... you can only put it in one
category. I'll tell you that's not true. ואמר רב כהנא, V'amar Rav
Kahana, Rav Kahana says, זומר וצריך לעצים, zomeir v'tzarich la-eitzim,
if somebody is pruning a tree and they want to also use
the wood that they're cutting down for firewood, חייב שתים, chayav shtayim,
that's two מלאכות. melachos. אחת משום נוטע ואחת משום קוצר, achas mishum
noteia v'achas mishum kotzeir,
one for planting, why planting? Because similar to like we said of
זורע, zoreia, because it's getting the tree to grow. נוטע noteia is
parallel to זורע zoreia by trees. You don't plant seeds, you plant
the tree. And it's קוצר kotzeir because what's קוצר? kotzeir? קוצר kotzeir
is cutting something that's growing because you want to use the thing,
like pulling a fruit off a tree. So here you're pulling wood
off a tree because you want the wood. So the Gemara says
קשיא, kashya, all right it's difficult, why there can you get a
double category and here not? But I gotta tell you the answer's
obvious. You know why? Because there you are actually having to do
two separate things with the same physical act. You're both and you
could have been, you know, either one could have been an independent
thing you would have done. You could have been cutting it to
make the tree grow and not interested in the wood. You could
have been cutting it for the wood and not interested in the
tree growing. You happen to be doing, achieving two goals with one
act, but it's really doing two separate things: harvesting the wood and
pruning the tree where you're doing them in the same act. So
that gets you two מלאכות. melachos. Whereas in this case, you're only
doing one thing. You're trying to weed the ground and water the
ground so that the plant will grow. There aren't two things that
you're doing. One thing. What does it mean when I water the
ground so the plant will grow? Which category to put that in?
So you can't put it in two categories. It's only one thing
you're doing, you only got to be in one category. You gotta
choose. Is that clear? The other thing, it was one physical act,
but you were really doing two separate things with that one act.
Here you're only doing one thing and you have to choose the
category to put it in. And that's the debate of רבה Raba
and רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. So the Gemara says like this: okay,
לרב יוסף קשיא, l'Rav Yosef kashya, I'm sorry I skipped a line,
קשיא. kashya. Okay, איתיבי רב יוסף לרבה. eiseivei Rav Yosef l'Raba. Now
רב
יוסף Rav Yosef
who said, who said
זורע, zoreia, challenges רבה. Raba. המנכש והמחפה בכלאים לוקה רבי עקיבא אומר
אף המקיים. ha-menakeish v'ha-mechapeh b'kilayim lokei Rabbi Akiva omer af ha-m'kayeim. If
somebody weeds the ground where כלאים kilayim is growing or covers it
up with dirt, the things that are growing, to help it grow,
you know if the like roots get exposed or something, then you
get lashes. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you get lashes even for
just allowing כלאים, kilayim, question about is it a לאו שאין בו
מעשה, lav she-ein bo ma'aseh, but okay, even just allowing כלאים kilayim
to grow. רש"י Rashi says somewhere else that you did something like
you made a fence around it to protect it. So even if
you didn't do anything about making it grow, but about protecting it
and allowing it, that you also get lashes. So let's look at
the first opinion. בשלמא לדידי, bishlama l'didi, according to me that I
say doing things with the ground is a form of planting, דאמינא
משום זורע, d'amina mishum zoreia, doing things to the ground is a
form of planting, היינו דאסירה זריעה בכלאים. hainu d'asira zeriah b'kilayim. That's
why, 'cause we know the Torah says שדך לא תזרע כלאים. sadcha
lo tizrah kilayim. You get lashes for planting. I consider that stuff
a form of planting. אלא לדידך דאמרת משום חורש, ela l'didach d'amart
mishum choreish, you don't call that in the category of planting. You
call that a type of furrowing. So חרישה בכלאים מי אסירא? charisha
b'kilayim mi asira? The Torah never says don't make furrows for כלאים.
kilayim. It says don't plant. So to you, how could you say
that somebody could get lashes for doing that? According to you, that's
not planting. אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to him, משום
מקיים. mishum m'kayeim. Yeah, the reason you get lashes there is not
because it's an act of planting, but because you're sustaining it, you're
protecting it. Okay, so the Gemara says one minute, that's what רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying. והא מדקתני סיפא, v'ha mi-d'katani seifa, the
end says, רבי עקיבא אומר אף המקיים, Rabbi Akiva omer af ha-m'kayeim,
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you get lashes not just for planting,
even for just letting them stay. מכלל דתנא קמא לאו משום מקיים
הוא. mi-khlal d'tana kamma lav mishum m'kayeim hu. So clearly the תנא
קמא tana kamma is more limiting. The תנא קמא tana kamma who
says no, letting them stay you don't get lashes, you only get
lashes for actually planting. So clearly that's the debate. You can't force
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva into the תנא קמא. tana kamma. To which
רבה Raba says back, watch me. So the Gemara says כולה רבי
עקיבא היא. kula Rabbi Akiva hi. Yes, it's all רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. ומה טעמא קאמר, u-mah ta'ama k'amar, and here you have to
read it as one thing. מה טעמא המנכש והמחפה בכלאים לוקה, mah
ta'ama ha-menakeish v'ha-mechapeh b'kilayim lokei, why do you get lashes for weeding
or for covering the dirt? Ah, that's not זורע, zoreia, so why
should you get lashes? משום
מקיים, mishum m'kayeim, not because of planting, it's not planting, but because
it is letting the כלאים kilayim and doing some act that lets
the כלאים kilayim stay around. שרבי עקיבא אומר אף המקיים, she-Rabbi Akiva
omer af ha-m'kayeim, even if you just let it stay around. מה
טעמא דרבי עקיבא, mah ta'amei d'Rabbi Akiva, what's his reasoning? דתניא, d'tanya,
as it's taught in a ברייתא, baraisa, שדך לא תזרע כלאים, sadcha
lo tizrah kilayim, don't plant it כלאים. kilayim. אין לי אלא זורע,
ein li ella zoreia, I only know you can't plant. מקיים מנין,
m'kayeim minayin, how do I know you can't even let it stay
around? תלמוד לומר כלאים שדך לא. talmud lomar kilayim sadcha lo. So
like a re-reading of the verse and tweaking the order, just don't
have כלאים kilayim in your field. Even if you don't plant it,
don't even let it be there. Okay, so clearly the simple sense
of this, of this is totally like רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. It
distinguishes it sees that working the dirt is a type of זורע,
zoreia, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is the opinion that says you
don't need to be
Is enough. רבא Rava rereads this to say it's all רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and insists that actually doing stuff with the dirt is
not a form of זורע. zore'a. Okay, so that is the debate
clearly. Again, this seems to side with רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, but
they're maintaining the two positions and we'll pick up tomorrow to see
how this ties into issues of our משנה mishna of watering the
plants on שמיטה shmita and watering the plants on חול המועד.